One of the most common ways of dividing the world
احد الاساليب المعتادة لتقسيم العالم
is into those who believe
هو الى قسم المؤمنين
and those who don't --
واولئك غير المؤمنين --
into the religious and the atheists.
الى المتدينين والملحدين
And for the last decade or so,
وحتى قرابة العقد الماضي
it's been quite clear
كان من الواضح
what being an atheist means.
مالذي يعنيه ان تكون ملحدا.
There have been some very vocal atheists
كان هناك بعض الاصوات شديدة الالحاد
who've pointed out,
,والذين اشاروا
not just that religion is wrong,
ليس فقط الى ان الدين خطأ
but that it's ridiculous.
بل أنه سخيف.
These people, many of whom have lived in North Oxford,
اولئك الاشخاص ,الكثير منهم ممن عاش في شمال اكسفورد
have argued --
تجادلوا --
they've argued that believing in God
حول ان الايمان بالله
is akin to believing in fairies
يشابه الايمان بالجن
and essentially that the whole thing
وبشكل اساسي هذا هو كل شيء
is a childish game.
انها لعبة طفولية.
Now I think it's too easy.
اظن الان انه من السهل جدا
I think it's too easy
اظن انه من السهل
to dismiss the whole of religion that way.
ان ترفض الدين باكمله بتلك الطريقة.
And it's as easy as shooting fish in a barrel.
ذلك بسهولة اقتناص سمكة في برميل.
And what I'd like to inaugurate today
والذي اريد ان افتتح به اليوم
is a new way of being an atheist --
هي طريقة جديدة لتكون ملحدا--
if you like, a new version of atheism
او اذا شئت ,نسخة جديدة من الإلحاد
we could call Atheism 2.0.
يمكنن تسميتها إلحاد 2.0
Now what is Atheism 2.0?
الان ما هو إلحاد 2.0
Well it starts from a very basic premise:
انه يبدأ من مقدمة اساسية:
of course, there's no God.
بالطبع , لا يوجد هناك إله
Of course, there are no deities or supernatural spirits
بالطبع, لا يوجد هناك الهة ولا ارواح خارقة
or angels, etc.
او ملائكة , الخ.
Now let's move on; that's not the end of the story,
الآن لنستمر, تلك ليست نهاية الحكاية,
that's the very, very beginning.
تلك هي البداية فقط
I'm interested in the kind of constituency
انا مهتم بهذا النوع من الانصار
that thinks something along these lines:
الذين يفكرون حول هذه الاسطر :
that thinks, "I can't believe in any of this stuff.
يفكرون , "لا استطيع الايمان بأي من تلك الاشياء.
I can't believe in the doctrines.
لا استطيع الايمان بالمذاهب.
I don't think these doctrines are right.
لا اعتقد ان تلك المذاهب صحيحه.
But," a very important but, "I love Christmas carols.
لكن," لكن هذه مهمة جدا , " احب تراتيل عيد الميلاد .
I really like the art of Mantegna.
احب فنون الفنان مانتيجنا.
I really like looking at old churches.
احب النظر الى الكنائس القديمة.
I really like turning the pages of the Old Testament."
احب تقليب اوراق كتب العهد القديم."
Whatever it may be,
ايا ما كان الامر,
you know the kind of thing I'm talking about --
انتم تعرفون اولئك الذين اتكلم عنهم --
people who are attracted to the ritualistic side,
الناس المنجذبين الى الجانب الشعائري,
the moralistic, communal side of religion,
الجانب , الاخلاقي , الطائفي من الدين
but can't bear the doctrine.
لكن لا يمكنهم تحمل المذهب
Until now, these people have faced a rather unpleasant choice.
حتى الان , هؤلاء الناس واجهوا خيارا غير سعيد
It's almost as though either you accept the doctrine
هو انه اما ان تقبل المذهب
and then you can have all the nice stuff,
ومن ثم تتمتع بكل الاشياء الجميلة,
or you reject the doctrine and
او ترفض المذهب ومن ثم
you're living in some kind of spiritual wasteland
تعيش في نوع من الضياع الروحي
under the guidance of CNN and Walmart.
تحت توجيه قناة سي ان ان و متاجر وول مارت.
So that's a sort of tough choice.
ذلك هو الخيار الصعب
I don't think we have to make that choice.
لا اعتقد ان علينا الاخذ بذلك الخيار.
I think there is an alternative.
اعتقد ان هناك بديل.
I think there are ways --
اعتقد ان هناك طرقا --
and I'm being both very respectful and completely impious --
وسوف اكون محترما وعاقا تماما --
of stealing from religions.
وانا اسرق من الاديان.
If you don't believe in a religion,
اذا كنت لا تؤمن بدين,
there's nothing wrong with picking and mixing,
لا توجد مشكلة في الاختيار والمزج,
with taking out the best sides of religion.
الاخذ بالجوانب الجيده من الدين.
And for me, atheism 2.0
وبالنسبة لي ,إلحاد 2.0
is about both, as I say,
هو عبارة عن ,كما اسلفت
a respectful and an impious way
طريقة محترمة وعاقة
of going through religions and saying, "What here could we use?"
للبحث في الاديان والقول ," مالذي يمكننا ان نستخدمه؟"
The secular world is full of holes.
العالم العلماني مليئ بالثقوب.
We have secularized badly, I would argue.
كنا علمانيين وبشدة ,واستطيع المجادلة في ذلك.
And a thorough study of religion
ودراسة شاملة للدين
could give us all sorts of insights
يمكنها ان تعطينا نوع من الرؤى
into areas of life that are not going too well.
حول مناطق من الحياة لا تسير بشكل جيد.
And I'd like to run through a few of these today.
وسوف اتجول خلال بعض منها اليوم.
I'd like to kick off by looking at education.
اريد الانطلاق من خلال النظر الى التعليم.
Now education is a field
التعليم هو مجال
the secular world really believes in.
يؤمن به العالم العلماني
When we think about how we're going to make the world a better place,
عندما نفكر كيف يمكننا جعل العالم مكانا افضل,
we think education; that's where we put a lot of money.
نعتقد انه التعليم , وهو ما نضع فيه الكثير من المال.
Education is going to give us, not only commercial skills, industrial skills,
التعليم لن يعطينا فقط مهارات تجارية,صناعية,
it's also going to make us better people.
سوف يجعلنا اشخاص افضل
You know the kind of thing a commencement address is, and graduation ceremonies,
تعرفون تلك العناوين في التخرج , وحفلات التخرج
those lyrical claims
تلك الادعاءت الشعرية
that education, the process of education -- particularly higher education --
ان التعليم , عملية التعليم -- وبالتحديد التعليم العالي --
will make us into nobler and better human beings.
سوف يجعلنا نبلاء واناس افضل.
That's a lovely idea.
تلك فكرة جميلة
Interesting where it came from.
من اين اتت.
In the early 19th century,
في اوائل القرن التاسع عشر
church attendance in Western Europe
مرتادي الكنيسة في غرب اوروبا
started sliding down very, very sharply, and people panicked.
بدأوا في الانحدار بشكل حاد , و فزع الناس.
They asked themselves the following question.
سألو انفسهم السؤال التالي.
They said, where are people going to find the morality,
قالوا , اين يمكن للناس ان يجدوا الاخلاقيات
where are they going to find guidance,
اين يمكنهم ان يجدو التوجيه,
and where are they going to find sources of consolation?
واين سوف يجدون مصادر المواساة؟
And influential voices came up with one answer.
وجاءت الاصوات المؤثرة بجواب واحد
They said culture.
قالو الثقافة.
It's to culture that we should look
الثقافة هي ما يجب ان نلتفت اليه
for guidance, for consolation, for morality.
للتوجيه , المواساة , الاخلاق
Let's look to the plays of Shakespeare,
لننظر الى مسرحيات شكسبير,
the dialogues of Plato, the novels of Jane Austen.
حوارات افلاطون , روايات جين اوستن.
In there, we'll find a lot of the truths
سوف نجد الكثير من الحقائق فيها
that we might previously have found in the Gospel of Saint John.
التي وجدناها سابقا في انجيل القديس جون.
Now I think that's a very beautiful idea and a very true idea.
اعتقد الان انها فكرة جميلة وفكرة صحيحة
They wanted to replace scripture with culture.
ارادو ان يستبدلوا الكتاب المقدس بالثقافة.
And that's a very plausible idea.
وتلك فكرة معقولة
It's also an idea that we have forgotten.
وفي نفس الوقت فكرة نسيناها.
If you went to a top university --
اذا ذهبت الى جامعة عريقة --
let's say you went to Harvard or Oxford or Cambridge --
مثل هارفارد ,اكسفورد , او كامبريدج --
and you said, "I've come here
وقلت "لقد اتيت الى هنا
because I'm in search of morality, guidance and consolation;
لأنني ابحث عن الاخلاقيات ,التوجيه , والمواساة,
I want to know how to live,"
اريد ان اعرف كيف اعيش,"
they would show you the way to the insane asylum.
سوف يدلوك على الطريق الى مستشفى المجانين.
This is simply not what our grandest and best institutes of higher learning
ذلك ببساط ما لا تهتم به
are in the business of.
مؤسسات تعليمنا العالي
Why? They don't think we need it.
لماذا؟ يعتقدون اننا لسنا في حاجة إليه.
They don't think we are in an urgent need of assistance.
هو لا يعتقدون اننا في حاجة ماسة للمساعدة
They see us as adults, rational adults.
هم ينظرون الينا كبالغين ,بالغين عاقلين.
What we need is information.
ما نحتاجه هو المعلومات.
We need data, we don't need help.
نحتاج البيانات, لا نحتاج المساعدة.
Now religions start from a very different place indeed.
في المقابل الاديان تبدأ من مكان مختلف جدا.
All religions, all major religions,
جميع الاديان , جميع الاديان الرئيسية
at various points call us children.
من نقاط متعددة تدعونا بالاطفال.
And like children,
وكالاطفال
they believe that we are in severe need of assistance.
يؤمنون اننا في حاجة ماسة للمساعدة.
We're only just holding it together.
نحن فقط نؤمن بهذا مجتمعين.
Perhaps this is just me, maybe you.
ربما انا فقط , ربما انتم.
But anyway, we're only just holding it together.
بأي حال نحن فقط نؤمن به .
And we need help. Of course, we need help.
ونحتاج المساعدة. بالطبع , نحتاج المساعدة.
And so we need guidance and we need didactic learning.
وبالتالي نحتاج توجيه ونحتاج تعليم منهجي
You know, in the 18th century in the U.K.,
تعرفون انه في القرن الثامن عشر في المملكة المتحدة,
the greatest preacher, greatest religious preacher, was a man called John Wesley,
ان اعظم واعظ, اعظم واعظ ديني , كان رجلا يدعى جون ويسلي
who went up and down this country delivering sermons,
والذي جاب البلاد يلقي المواعظ
advising people how they could live.
ينصح الناس كيف يمكنهم العيش.
He delivered sermons on the duties of parents to their children
كان يلقي المواعظ عن حقوق الاطفال على ابائهم
and children to their parents,
وحقوق الاباء على ابنائهم
the duties of the rich to the poor and the poor to the rich.
وحقوق الفقراء على الاغنياء وحقوق الفقراء على الاغنياء
He was trying to tell people how they should live
كان يحاول اخبار الناس كيف يمكنهم ان يعيشوا
through the medium of sermons,
عبر المواعظ
the classic medium of delivery of religions.
الطريقة التقليدية لايصال الاديان
Now we've given up with the idea of sermons.
الان مللنا من فكرة المواعظ
If you said to a modern liberal individualist,
اذا قلت لشخص لبرالي مستقل,
"Hey, how about a sermon?"
"ما رايك في موعظة ؟"
they'd go, "No, no. I don't need one of those.
ستكون الاجابة ," لا ,لا ,لا احتاج لها.
I'm an independent, individual person."
انا انسان مستقل ."
What's the difference between a sermon
مالفرق بين الموعظة
and our modern, secular mode of delivery, the lecture?
وطريقتنا العلمانية الحديثة في ايصال المعلومة وهي المحاضرة؟
Well a sermon wants to change your life
حسنا الموعظة تريد ان تغير حياتك
and a lecture wants to give you a bit of information.
والمحاضرة تريد ان تعطيك معلومات
And I think we need to get back to that sermon tradition.
واعتقد انه يجب علينا ان نعود الى تقليد المواعظ
The tradition of sermonizing is hugely valuable,
تقليد الوعظ ذو قيمة عالية
because we are in need of guidance,
لأننا في حاجة للتوجيه,
morality and consolation --
اخلاقيات, ومواساة
and religions know that.
والاديان تعرف ذلك.
Another point about education:
نقطة اخرى عن التعليم:
we tend to believe in the modern secular world
نحن نتجه للايمان بالعالم العلماني
that if you tell someone something once, they'll remember it.
حيث انك اذا اخبرت شخص ما عن شيء ما لمرة واحدة , سوف يتذكره
Sit them in a classroom, tell them about Plato
اجلسهم في فصل دراسي, اخبرهم عن افلاطون
at the age of 20, send them out for a career in management consultancy for 40 years,
في العشرين من العمر , ارسلهم للحصول على شهادة في الاستشارات الاداريه في عمر الاربعين
and that lesson will stick with them.
سوف يلصق معهم هذا الدرس.
Religions go, "Nonsense.
بينما في الدين ,"ذلك لا معنى له .
You need to keep repeating the lesson 10 times a day.
عليك تكرار الدرس عشر مرات في اليوم .
So get on your knees and repeat it."
اذا انزل على ركبتيك وكرره." أركع
That's what all religions tell us:
هذا ما يخبرنا به جميع الاديان :
"Get on you knees and repeat it 10 or 20 or 15 times a day."
"انزل على ركبتيك وكرر 10 او 20 او 15 مرة يوميا."
Otherwise our minds are like sieves.
والا فان عقولنا مثل الغرابيل .
So religions are cultures of repetition.
اذا الاديان هي ثقافة التكرار.
They circle the great truths again and again and again.
يعيدون تدوير الحقائق العظيمة مرارا ومرارا وتكرارا.
We associate repetition with boredom.
نحن نربط التكرار بالملل.
"Give us the new," we're always saying.
"اعطني الجديد" هذا ما نقوله دائما.
"The new is better than the old."
"الجديد افضل من القديم."
If I said to you, "Okay, we're not going to have new TED.
لو قلت لكم ," حسنا لن يكون لدينا اي جديد في تيد"
We're just going to run through all the old ones
سوف نعيد كل الاشياء القديمة
and watch them five times because they're so true.
ونشاهدها خمس مرات لانها حقيقية جدا.
We're going to watch Elizabeth Gilbert five times
سوف نشاهد اليزبيث حيلبيرت خمس مرات
because what she says is so clever," you'd feel cheated.
لأن ما تقوله ذكي جدا," سوف تشعر بانك خدعت.
Not so if you're adopting a religious mindset.
لن يكون ذلك هو الحال اذا كنت ممن يتبنون العقلية الدينية
The other things that religions do
الشيء الاخر الذي تفعله الاديان
is to arrange time.
هي ترتيب الوقت.
All the major religions give us calendars.
جميع الاديان الرئيسية تعطينا تقويم
What is a calendar?
ماهو التقويم؟
A calendar is a way of making sure that across the year
التقويم هو طريقة للتاكد انه خلال السنة
you will bump into certain very important ideas.
سوف تملاء بأفكار مهمة جوهرية
In the Catholic chronology, Catholic calendar,
في التوقيت الكاثوليكي , التقويم الكاثوليكي,
at the end of March you will think about St. Jerome
في نهاية شهر مارس سوف تفكر في القديس جيروم
and his qualities of humility and goodness
وصفاته من ناحية التواضع و الصلاح
and his generosity to the poor.
وكرمه تجاه الفقراء
You won't do that by accident; you will do that because you are guided to do that.
لا تفعل ذلك بمحظ الصدفة ,سوف تفعله لأنه تم توجيهك لتفعل ذلك
Now we don't think that way.
نحن الان لا نفكر بهذه الطريقة
In the secular world we think, "If an idea is important, I'll bump into it.
في عالم العلمانية," اذ كانت الفكرة مهمة ,سوف أهتم بها.
I'll just come across it."
سوف امضي فيها فورا."
Nonsense, says the religious world view.
ذلك هراء من وجهة نظر العالم المتدين.
Religious view says we need calendars, we need to structure time,
وجهة النظر الدينية تقول اننا نحتاج الى تقويم زمني , نحتاج الى هيكل زمني,
we need to synchronize encounters.
نحتاج الى مزامنة اللقاءت
This comes across also
هذا يقودنا ايضا
in the way in which religions set up rituals
الى الطريقة التي تنظم في الاديان الطقوس
around important feelings.
حول المشاعر الهامة
Take the Moon. It's really important to look at the Moon.
خذ القمر, من المهم حقا ان تنظر الى القمر.
You know, when you look at the Moon,
تعلم انه حين تنظر الى القمر,
you think, "I'm really small. What are my problems?"
تشعر," انني حقا صغير, ماهي مشاكلي؟"
It sets things into perspective, etc., etc.
تنتظم الاشياء في منظور , الخ ,الخ.
We should all look at the Moon a bit more often. We don't.
يجب ان ننظر الى القمر بصورة اكثر. نحن لا نفعل ذلك
Why don't we? Well there's nothing to tell us, "Look at the Moon."
لماذا لا نفعل؟ لانه لا يوجد شيئ يخبرنا ," انظر الى القمر ."
But if you're a Zen Buddhist in the middle of September,
لكنك اذا كنت بوذيا في منتصف شهر سبتمبر,
you will be ordered out of your home, made to stand on a canonical platform
سوف تكون مأمورا ان تخرج من منزلك لتقف فوق مكان للتعبد
and made to celebrate the festival of Tsukimi,
وتحتفل باحتفال تسوكيمي
where you will be given poems to read
حيث سيتم اعطاءك قصائد لتقرأها
in honor of the Moon and the passage of time
على شرف القمر ومرور الزمن
and the frailty of life that it should remind us of.
وهشاشة الحياة التي يجب تذكيرنا به.
You'll be handed rice cakes.
سوف تتناول كيكة الارز.
And the Moon and the reflection on the Moon
والقمر وانعكاس القمر
will have a secure place in your heart.
سوف يكون له مكانة امنة في قلبك
That's very good.
ذلك جيد جدا.
The other thing that religions are really aware of
الشيء الاخر الذي تهتم به الاديان
is: speak well --
هو اتقان التحدث --
I'm not doing a very good job of this here --
انا لا اقوم بعمل جيد من ذلك القبيل هنا --
but oratory, oratory is absolutely key to religions.
لكن فن الخطابة هو مفتاح الدين بشكل مطلق.
In the secular world, you can come through the university system and be a lousy speaker
في العالم العلماني ,ستمضي في نظام الجامعة وتكون متحدث فاشل
and still have a great career.
لكن ما زال بامكانك الحصول على درجة علمية
But the religious world doesn't think that way.
لكن العالم الديني لا يفكر بنفس الطريقة
What you're saying needs to be backed up
ما تقوله يجب ان يغلف
by a really convincing way of saying it.
بطريقة مقنعة في قوله
So if you go to an African-American Pentecostalist church
فلو ذهبت الى كنيسه امريكية افريقية
in the American South
في الجنوب الامريكي
and you listen to how they talk,
واستمعت الى الطريقة التي يتكلمون بها
my goodness, they talk well.
يا الهي انهم يتحدثثون بطلاقة
After every convincing point, people will go, "Amen, amen, amen."
بعد كل نقطة مقنعة سوف يقول الناس , " امين ,امين ,امين"
At the end of a really rousing paragraph, they'll all stand up,
بعد نهاية الفقرة المثيرة سوف يقفون,
and they'll go, "Thank you Jesus, thank you Christ, thank you Savior."
ويقولون ," شكرا لك يا عيسى , شكرا للمسيح, شكرا للمنقذ."
If we were doing it like they do it --
لو قمنا بذلك بنفس العمل نفس طريقتهم --
let's not do it, but if we were to do it --
لن نقوم بذلك,لكن لو قمنا به بنفس الطريقة--
I would tell you something like, "Culture should replace scripture."
ساقول لكم شيئ من قبيل ," الثقافة يجب ان تحل محل الكتاب المقدس."
And you would go, "Amen, amen, amen."
وستقولون , "امين ,امين ,امين ."
And at the end of my talk, you would all stand up
وفي نهاية خطابي , سوف تقفون جميعا
and you would go, "Thank you Plato, thank you Shakespeare, thank you Jane Austen."
وسوف تقولون ," شكرا لك يا افلاطون,شكرا لك يا شكسبير , وشكرا لك يا جين اوستن"
And we'd know that we had a real rhythm going.
وسيكون لدينا ايقاع حقيقي
All right, all right. We're getting there. We're getting there.
حسنا حسنا ,نحن نلحقهم ,نحن نلحقهم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The other thing that religions know is we're not just brains,
الشيئ الاخر الذي تدركه الاديان اننا لسنا عقول فقط
we are also bodies.
لكننا ايضا اجساد
And when they teach us a lesson,
وعندما يعلمونا درسا,
they do it via the body.
يعلمونا له من خلال الجسد
So for example,
على سبيل المثال,
take the Jewish idea of forgiveness.
خذو الفكرة اليهودية عن التسامح.
Jews are very interested in forgiveness
اليهود مهتمون جدا بالتسامح
and how we should start anew and start afresh.
وكيف يمكننا البدء من جديد و بنقاء
They don't just deliver us sermons on this.
هم فقط لا يعطونا مواعظ عن ذلك
They don't just give us books or words about this.
هم لا يعطونا فقط كتب وكلمات عن ذلك
They tell us to have a bath.
يخبروننا ان نأخذ حماما
So in Orthodox Jewish communities, every Friday you go to a Mikveh.
ففي مجتعات اليهود الارثوذوكس ,في كل جمعة يجب ان تذهب الى ميكفه
You immerse yourself in the water,
تغمر نفسك في الماء
and a physical action backs up a philosophical idea.
وتغلف فكرة فلسفية بفعل مادي
We don't tend to do that.
نحن لا نقوم بفعل ذلك
Our ideas are in one area and our behavior with our bodies is in another.
افكارنا في منطقة وسلوكنا مع اجسادنا في منطقة اخرى
Religions are fascinating in the way they try and combine the two.
الاديان ساحرة في الطريقة التي تجمع بها الاثنان.
Let's look at art now.
لننظر الى الفن الان
Now art is something that in the secular world,
الفن هو شيء في العالم العلماني
we think very highly of. We think art is really, really important.
نفكر فيه بشدة.نفكر انه شي حقا مهم
A lot of our surplus wealth goes to museums, etc.
والكثيرون منا من فاحشي الثراء يذهبون الى المتاحف,الخ.
We sometimes hear it said
ونسمعهم احيانا يقولون
that museums are our new cathedrals, or our new churches.
المتاحف هي كاتدرائيتنا الجديدة. كنائسنا الجديدة.
You've heard that saying.
سمعتم ذلك القول
Now I think that the potential is there,
الان اعتقد ان القوة تكمن هناك
but we've completely let ourselves down.
لكننا نحبط انفسنا
And the reason we've let ourselves down
والسبب في ترك انفسنا نحبط
is that we're not properly studying
اننا لا ندرس بصورة كافية
how religions handle art.
كيف تتعامل الاديان مع الفن
The two really bad ideas that are hovering in the modern world
اسوأ فكرتين تحومان في العالم الحديث
that inhibit our capacity to draw strength from art:
كبح جماحنا من اكتساب قوتنا من الفن
The first idea is that art should be for art's sake --
الفكرة الاولى ان الفن يجب ان يكون لغرض الفن
a ridiculous idea --
فكرة سخيفة
an idea that art should live in a hermetic bubble
فكرة ان الفن يجب ان يكون في فقاعة محكمة
and should not try to do anything with this troubled world.
ولا يجب ان يفعل شيئ لاجل هذا العالم المضطرب
I couldn't disagree more.
لا يمكنني عدم الموافقة اكثر من ذلك
The other thing that we believe is that art shouldn't explain itself,
الشيئ الاخر الذي نؤمن به هو ان الفن لا يجب ان يشرح نفسه
that artists shouldn't say what they're up to,
الفنان لا يتوجب عليه قول ما يرمز له
because if they said it, it might destroy the spell
لانهم لو قالوا لربما ازالوا السحر
and we might find it too easy.
ولربما اصبح سهلا بالنسبة لنا
That's why a very common feeling when you're in a museum --
وذلك هو سبب الشعور المعتاد عندما تزور متحف --
let's admit it --
لنعترف بذلك --
is, "I don't know what this is about."
وهو ," لا اعرف مالذي يعنيه هذا ."
But if we're serious people, we don't admit to that.
لكن اذا كنا اناس جادين , لن نعترف بذلك.
But that feeling of puzzlement is structural
لكن ذلك الشعور المحير , هيكلي
to contemporary art.
للفن المعاصر.
Now religions have a much saner attitude to art.
الاديان لديها موقف اكثر عقلانية تجاه الفن
They have no trouble telling us what art is about.
ليس لديهم مشكله في اخبارنا مالذي يعنيه الفن
Art is about two things in all the major faiths.
الفن يدور حول شيئين في الاديان الرئيسية
Firstly, it's trying to remind you
اولا , يحاول تذكيرك
of what there is to love.
بالذي تحبه
And secondly, it's trying to remind you
ثانيا: يحاول تذكيرك
of what there is to fear and to hate.
بالذي تخشاه وتكرهه
And that's what art is.
وهذا ما يعنيه الفن
Art is a visceral encounter with the most important ideas of your faith.
الفن هو محشو بالافكار الاكثر اهمية لايمانك
So as you walk around a church,
فعندما تتجول في كنيسة
or a mosque or a cathedral,
او مسجد او كاتدرائية
what you're trying to imbibe, what you're imbibing is,
ما تحاول تشربه ,الذي تتشربه هو,
through your eyes, through your senses,
خلال عينيك ,خلال حواسك,
truths that have otherwise come to you through your mind.
الحقائق التي سوف تصلك بشكل اخر عن طريق عقلك.
Essentially it's propaganda.
انها دعاية بشكل اساسي
Rembrandt is a propagandist
الفنان ريمبراندت ممارس للدعاية
in the Christian view.
من وجهة نظر مسيحية
Now the word "propaganda" sets off alarm bells.
الان كلمة "دعاية" تعطل اجراس الانذار
We think of Hitler, we think of Stalin. Don't, necessarily.
نفكر في هتلر , نفكر في ستالين. لا تفعل ,بالضرورة
Propaganda is a manner of being didactic in honor of something.
الدعاية هو اسلوب الانتماء لشرف شيئ ما
And if that thing is good, there's no problem with it at all.
واذا كان ذلك الشيء جيدا فلا مشكلة في ذلك
My view is that museums should take a leaf out of the book of religions.
وجهة نظري ,ان المتاحف يجب ان تنتزع ورقة من كتاب الاديان
And they should make sure that when you walk into a museum --
وان يكونوا متأكدين انه عندما نتجول في متحف--
if I was a museum curator,
في حال كنت امين متحف,
I would make a room for love, a room for generosity.
سوف اجعل غرفة للحب ,غرفة للكرم
All works of art are talking to us about things.
جميع الاعمال تتحدث عن اشياء
And if we were able to arrange spaces
واذا استطعنا ان ننظم المساحات
where we could come across works
حيث نتجول خلال الاعمال
where we would be told, use these works of art
بحيث نكون على علم باستخدام تلك الاعمال الفنية
to cement these ideas in your mind,
لنرسخ تلك الافكار في عقلك
we would get a lot more out of art.
سوف نحصل على الكثير من الفن
Art would pick up the duty that it used to have
الفن سوف يمارس الواجب الذي اعتاد ان يمارسه
and that we've neglected because of certain mis-founded ideas.
والذي اهملناه بسبب صعوبة فهم الافكار
Art should be one of the tools
الفن يجب ان يكون احد الادوات
by which we improve our society.
التي نطور مجتمعنا من خلاله
Art should be didactic.
الفن يجب ان يكون تعليمي
Let's think of something else.
لنفكر في شي اخر
The people in the modern world, in the secular world,
الناس في العالم المتحضر , في العالم العلماني
who are interested in matters of the spirit,
والمهتمين بمسائل الروح
in matters of the mind,
ومسائل العقل.
in higher soul-like concerns,
ومسائل ماشابه الروح
tend to be isolated individuals.
يصبحون افراد معزولين
They're poets, they're philosophers, they're photographers, they're filmmakers.
منهم الشعراء, منهم الفلاسفة,منهم المصورون,منهم صانعي الافلام
And they tend to be on their own.
ويتجهون ليستقلوا بانفسهم
They're our cottage industries. They are vulnerable, single people.
هم اكواخنا الصناعية, ضعفاء, افراد
And they get depressed and they get sad on their own.
ويصبحون مكتئبين , وحزينين بمفردهم
And they don't really change much.
ولا يتغيرون كثيرا
Now think about religions, think about organized religions.
الان فكر في الاديان , فكر في الاديان المنظمة
What do organized religions do?
مالذي تفعله الاديان المنظمة؟
They group together, they form institutions.
يتجمعون معا, ينشئون مؤسسات
And that has all sorts of advantages.
تمتلك كل المميزات
First of all, scale, might.
اولا وقبل كل شيء ,حجم و طاقة ضخمة
The Catholic Church pulled in 97 billion dollars last year
الكنيسة الكاثوليكية صرفت 97 بليون دولار في العام الماضي
according to the Wall Street Journal.
وفقا لصحيفة وول ستريت جورنال
These are massive machines.
انها مكائن هائلة.
They're collaborative, they're branded, they're multinational,
انها تعاونية, انها معروفة, انها متعددة الجنسيات
and they're highly disciplined.
وهي منضبطة بشكل عالي
These are all very good qualities.
تلك قيم عالية
We recognize them in relation to corporations.
نلاحظهم بعلاقتهم بالشركات
And corporations are very like religions in many ways,
والشركات هي كالاديان في عدة نواحي
except they're right down at the bottom of the pyramid of needs.
ماعدا انهم في اسفل هرم الاحتياجات
They're selling us shoes and cars.
يبيعوننا الاحذية والسيارات
Whereas the people who are selling us the higher stuff --
بينما الناس الذين يبيعون اشياء اعلى مقاما
the therapists, the poets --
المعالجون , الشعراء--
are on their own and they have no power,
هم بمفردهم وليس لديهم قوة
they have no might.
ولا طاقة
So religions are the foremost example
اذا الاديان قبل كل شيئ هي مثال
of an institution that is fighting for the things of the mind.
على مؤسسة تقاتل في سبيل اشياء متعلقه بالعقل
Now we may not agree with what religions are trying to teach us,
الان لربما نحن غير موافقين على ما تحاول الاديان تعليمه لنا,
but we can admire the institutional way
ولكن يمكننا الاعجاب بنهجهم المؤسساتي
in which they're doing it.
الذي يقومون به
Books alone, books written by lone individuals,
الكتب وحدها, الكتب المكتوبه من افراد وحيدين,
are not going to change anything.
لن تغير شيء
We need to group together.
يجب ان نجتمع معا
If you want to change the world, you have to group together, you have to be collaborative.
اذا اردت تغيير العالم, يجب ان تتجمعوا معا, يجب ان تكونوا متعاونين
And that's what religions do.
وهذا ما تفعله الاديان
They are multinational, as I say,
انهم متعددي الجنسيات كم اسلفت
they are branded, they have a clear identity,
انهم معروفين ولهم هوية واضحة
so they don't get lost in a busy world.
وبالتالي لا يضيعون في عالم مشغول
That's something we can learn from.
ذلك شيء يمكننا تعلمه منهم
I want to conclude.
اريد ان اختم
Really what I want to say
الذي اريد قوله حقيقةً
is for many of you who are operating in a range of different fields,
للكثير منكم من الذين يعملون في مجالات مختلفة
there is something to learn from the example of religion --
هناك شيء لنتعلمه من مثال الدين--
even if you don't believe any of it.
حتى ولو لم تكن تؤمن بأي واحد
If you're involved in anything that's communal,
اذا كنت تعمل بشيء طائفي
that involves lots of people getting together,
يستدعي وجود الكثير من الناس يجتمعون معا
there are things for you in religion.
هناك اشياء تفيدك في الدين.
If you're involved, say, in a travel industry in any way,
ان كنت تعمل في صناعة السفر بأي شكل,
look at pilgrimage.
انظر الى الحج
Look very closely at pilgrimage.
انظر الى الحج بعمق
We haven't begun to scratch the surface
لم نبدأ من ادنى مستوى
of what travel could be
لما يمكن ان يعنيه السفر
because we haven't looked at what religions do with travel.
لأننا لم ننظر لما تفعله الاديان تجاه السفر
If you're in the art world,
اذا كنت في عالم الفن
look at the example of what religions are doing with art.
انظر الى المثال حول مالذي تفعله الاديان بالفن
And if you're an educator in any way,
واذا كنت اكاديمي
again, look at how religions are spreading ideas.
مرة اخرى انظر كيف تقوم الاديان بالحديث عن الافكار
You may not agree with the ideas,
لربما لا توافق على الافكار
but my goodness, they're highly effective mechanisms for doing so.
لكنها ذات فعالية عالية في ذلك المجال
So really my concluding point
لذلك فان نقطة استنتاجي
is you may not agree with religion,
انه ربما لا تتفق مع الدين
but at the end of the day,
لكن في نهاية اليوم,
religions are so subtle, so complicated,
الاديان رقيقة,ومعقدة,
so intelligent in many ways
ذكية جدا في نواحي عدة
that they're not fit to be abandoned to the religious alone;
بحيث لا يمكن تركها لمتدينين فقط
they're for all of us.
انها لنا جميعا
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Now this is actually a courageous talk,
كريس اندرسون: حقا ذلك فعلا حديث شجاع,
because you're kind of setting up yourself in some ways
لانك وضعت نفسك باشكال عده
to be ridiculed in some quarters.
في وضع الساخر في بعض المواضع
AB: You can get shot by both sides.
الين : سوف يطلق عليك النار من الجانبين,
You can get shot by the hard-headed atheists,
سوف يطلق عليك النار من الملحدين ذو العقول الجامدة
and you can get shot by those who fully believe.
ومن اؤلئك المؤمنين
CA: Incoming missiles from North Oxford at any moment.
كريس : صواريخ قادمة من شمال اكسفورد في اي لحظة
AB: Indeed.
اليان: بالطبع
CA: But you left out one aspect of religion
كريس :لكنك لم تتطرق لاحد مظاهر الدين
that a lot of people might say
ذلك ان الكثير من الناس يمكن ان يقولوا
your agenda could borrow from,
يمكن لاجندتك ان تستعيره
which is this sense --
وهو ذو معنى--
that's actually probably the most important thing to anyone who's religious --
انه في الواقع ربما الشئ الاكثر اهمية لاي شخص متدين--
of spiritual experience,
وبممارسة روحية,
of some kind of connection
على ارتباط بشكل ما
with something that's bigger than you are.
بشيء اعظم منك
Is there any room for that experience in Atheism 2.0?
هل هناك مرادف لذلك الشيء في إلحاد 2.0؟
AB: Absolutely. I, like many of you, meet people
اليان :بالطبع,انا مثل الكثير منكم,اقابل الناس
who say things like, "But isn't there something bigger than us,
ممن يقولون اشياء مثل,"لكن الا يوجد شيء اكبر منا,
something else?"
شيء اخر؟"
And I say, "Of course." And they say, "So aren't you sort of religious?"
واقول :"بالطبع" ويقولون," اليس ذلك نوع من التدين؟"
And I go, "No." Why does that sense of mystery,
واجيب ,"لا " لماذا ذلك الشعور بالغرابة
that sense of the dizzying scale of the universe,
ذلك الشعور بالمقاييس المذهلة للكون,
need to be accompanied by a mystical feeling?
تحتاج ان تترافق مع شعور صوفي؟
Science and just observation
العلم والتأمل
gives us that feeling without it,
يعطينا ذلك الشعرو بدون تصوف
so I don't feel the need.
لذلك لا اشعر بالحاجة
The universe is large and we are tiny,
الكون كبير ونحن ضئيلين
without the need for further religious superstructure.
بدون الحاجة للمزيد من الفوقية الدينية
So one can have so-called spiritual moments
لذلك احدهم صادف لحظة روحية
without belief in the spirit.
بدون الايمان بالروح
CA: Actually, let me just ask a question.
كريس: دعني اسألك سؤالا.
How many people here would say
كم من الاشخاص هنا يمكن ان يقولوا
that religion is important to them?
الدين مهم لهم؟
Is there an equivalent process
هل هناك عملية مساوية
by which there's a sort of bridge
هل يوجد جسر
between what you're talking about and what you would say to them?
بين ما تتحدث عنه وما يمكن ان تقوله لهم؟
AB: I would say that there are many, many gaps in secular life
اليان: سـأقول ان هنام الكثير والكثير من الفجوات في الحياة العلمانية
and these can be plugged.
والتي يمكن سدها
It's not as though, as I try to suggest,
انها ليس كاقترح
it's not as though either you have religion
وليس بان يكون لديك دين
and then you have to accept all sorts of things,
ومن ثم تتقبل جميع اشكال الاشياء
or you don't have religion
او لا يكون لديك دين
and then you're cut off from all these very good things.
ومن ثم تنقطع عن كل تلك الاشياء الجيدة
It's so sad that we constantly say,
انه من المحزن ان ندأب على القول,
"I don't believe so I can't have community,
"انا لا اؤمن ومن ثم لا استطيع ان يكون لي جماعة,
so I'm cut off from morality,
لذلك انا منسلخ من الاخلاقيات,
so I can't go on a pilgrimage."
لذلك لا يمكنني الذهاب للحج."
One wants to say, "Nonsense. Why not?"
احدهم يمكن ان يقول ," هراء .لما لا؟"
And that's really the spirit of my talk.
وذلك هو فعلا روح حديثي
There's so much we can absorb.
هناك الكثير يمكننا امتصاصه
Atheism shouldn't cut itself off from the rich sources of religion.
الالحاد يجب ان لا يسلخ نفسه من المصادر الغنية للدين
CA: It seems to me that there's plenty of people in the TED community
كريس:يبدو بالنسبة لي ان الكثير من مجتمع تيد
who are atheists.
من الملحدين
But probably most people in the community
لكن ربما معظم الناس في هذا المجتمع
certainly don't think that religion is going away any time soon
حقيقة لا يعتقدون ان الدين يمكن ان يختفي قريبا
and want to find the language
ويريدون ان يجدوا اللغة
to have a constructive dialogue
للحصول على حوار بناء
and to feel like we can actually talk to each other
وليشعرو انهم بالفعل يمكن ان نتحاور معا
and at least share some things in common.
واخيرا مشاركة بعض الاشياء معا.
Are we foolish to be optimistic
هل نحن اغبياء بهذا التفاؤل
about the possibility of a world
حول امكانية وجود عالم
where, instead of religion being the great rallying cry
حيث بدلا من ان يكون الدين عباره عن منافسات على الصراخ
of divide and war,
حول الانقسام والحرب,
that there could be bridging?
هل يمكن ان يكون هناك جسر؟
AB: No, we need to be polite about differences.
اليان : لا , يجب ان نكون مؤدبين تجاه الاختلافات
Politeness is a much-overlooked virtue.
التأدب يطغى على الفضيلة
It's seen as hypocrisy.
ذلك يبدو كنفاق
But we need to get to a stage when you're an atheist
لكن ما نريده ان نصل لمستوى بحيث ان اذا كنت ملحدا
and someone says, "Well you know, I did pray the other day,"
وقال احدهم ," هل تعلم. لقد صليت لليوم الاخر,"
you politely ignore it.
ان تتجاهله بأدب
You move on.
وتواصل طريقك
Because you've agreed on 90 percent of things,
لانكم اتفقتم على 90 بالمئة من الاشياء
because you have a shared view on so many things,
لانكم تشاركتم جهات النظر حول الكثير من الاشياء
and you politely differ.
وانتم مختلفون بأدب
And I think that's what the religious wars of late have ignored.
وهذا في اعتقادي الذي تجاهلته الحروب الدينية المتأخرة
They've ignored the possibility of harmonious disagreement.
لقد تجاهلوا عدم التوافق المتناغم
CA: And finally, does this new thing that you're proposing
كريس: واخيرا هل هذا شيء جديد تقترحه
that's not a religion but something else,
والذي هو ليس دين ولكنه شيء اخر
does it need a leader,
هل يحتاج قائد
and are you volunteering to be the pope?
وهل تتطوع لتكون البابا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
AB: Well, one thing that we're all very suspicious of
اليان :احد الاشياء التي نرتاب حولها
is individual leaders.
هو القادة المتفردون
It doesn't need it.
لا يحتاجه
What I've tried to lay out is a framework
ما حاولت عرضه هو اطار العمل
and I'm hoping that people can just fill it in.
واتمنى ان يتمكن الناس من شغله
I've sketched a sort of broad framework.
رسمت ما يشبه إطار العمل العريض
But wherever you are, as I say, if you're in the travel industry, do that travel bit.
لكن ايا ما كنت , كما اقول , لو كنت في صناعة السفر, قم بعمل الجزء المتعلق بالسفر
If you're in the communal industry, look at religion and do the communal bit.
اذا كنت في قطاع جماعي , انظر الى الدين وطبق الجزء الجماعي
So it's a wiki project.
اذا هو مشروع يقبل المشاركة "ويكي"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
CA: Alain, thank you for sparking many conversations later.
كريس: اليان, شكرا لاثارتك الكثير من النقاشات لاحقا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)